<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Java | derjan]]></title>
  <link href="http://derjan.io/blog/categories/java/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://derjan.io/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-27T12:17:09+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://derjan.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jan Ehrhardt]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First steps with Groovy's invokedynamic support]]></title>
    <link href="http://derjan.io/blog/2012/08/08/first-steps-with-groovys-invokedynamic-support/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-08T07:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://derjan.io/blog/2012/08/08/first-steps-with-groovys-invokedynamic-support</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is not really new, but
<a href="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/GROOVY/2012/06/28/Groovy+2.0+released">Groovy 2.0 is out</a>.
There is even a version
<a href="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/GROOVY/2012/06/28/Groovy+2.0+released">2.0.1 released</a>,
which only fixes some bugs. One of the new features introduced with
version 2.0 is support for invokedynamic. But it is not used by
default, instead you have to activate it. But there is only few
documentation and it is spread over the web. So how do we use
invokedynamic in our code?</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Get your machine ready</h2>

<p>First of all you should have installed
<a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/index.html">Java 7</a>,
since invokedynamic is not available in earlier versions of Java. The
easiest way to test invokedynamic support is by using the command
line, so should also have installed
<a href="http://groovy.codehaus.org/Download">Groovy 2.0</a> or later.</p>

<p>Having Groovy installed you could simply use it with the <em>groovy</em>
command in your terminal, but a different way, you should be familiar
with is to compile Groovy code with <em>groovyc</em> to Java byte code. The
byte code can be executed with <em>java -classpath</em>.</p>

<p><code>bash
wget -O HelloWorld.groovy https://raw.github.com/gist/3292829/f9d2a37c6cdc45570aab1bf0ce665262899a0dde/HelloWorld.java
groovyc HelloWorld.groovy
java -classpath .:$GROOVY_HOME/embeddable/groovy-all-2.0.1.jar HelloWorld
</code></p>

<p>These steps are pretty similar to my
<a href="https://gist.github.com/3292829">first steps with Java</a> years ago and
they are necessary to do your first steps with invokedynamic. But at
this time there is no invokedynamic involved.</p>

<h2>Two steps to use invokedynamic</h2>

<p>The first step on our way to invokedynamic is using the right Groovy
JAR, while executing our byte code. In <em>$GROOVY_HOME/embeddable/</em> you
can find <em>groovy-all-2.0.1-indy.jar</em>, where indy is short for
invokedynamic. This JAR contains a version of Groovy, that uses
invokedynamic instead of Groovy's very own old dynamic invoking code.</p>

<p>Using the indy JAR is not enough, since everything should still work
under Java 5 or 6, even this JAR is used. The byte code created by
Groovy compiler is not using any Java 7 features. So the second step
is to tell the <em>groovyc</em> command to compile our Groovy code using
invokedynamic by adding the <em>--indy</em> flag. The above sample should now
look like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
wget -O HelloWorld.groovy https://raw.github.com/gist/3292829/f9d2a37c6cdc45570aab1bf0ce665262899a0dde/HelloWorld.java
groovyc --indy HelloWorld.groovy
java -classpath .:$GROOVY_HOME/embeddable/groovy-all-2.0.1-indy.jar HelloWorld
</code></p>

<h2>Make your Groovy 2.0 indy</h2>

<p>Running the above code will fail at second command with a curious
exception:</p>

<p><code>
groovy.lang.GroovyRuntimeException: Cannot use invokedynamic, indy module was excluded from this build.
</code></p>

<p>What went wrong? Didn't I use Groovy 2.0? Didn't I pass the <em>--indy</em>
flag correctly? The
<a href="http://permalink.gmane.org/gmane.comp.lang.groovy.devel/26698">solution</a>
is simple, once you understand your Groovy installation. The Groovy
JARs used by <em>groovyc</em> are in <em>$GROOVY_HOME/lib/</em>, but the indy JARs
are in <em>$GROOVY_HOME/indy/</em>. So replace the Groovy JAR with the indy
version.</p>

<p><code>bash
cd $GROOVY_HOME
cp -R lib lib.org
cp indy/groovy-2.0.1-indy.jar lib/groovy-2.0.1.jar
</code></p>

<p>Now the above sample should work, but it really looks like the Groovy
developers do not want you to use invokedynamic. They made it as
difficult as possible, but why?</p>

<h2>Loosing previous optimizations with invokedynamic</h2>

<p>The Groovy developers have spent a lot of time to get Groovy's runtime
faster. One great step was the primitive optimization introduced with
Groovy 1.8. But these optimizations are not available if everything is
delegated to the JVM, what happens with invokedynamic.</p>

<p>You can test it using a simple
<a href="https://gist.github.com/3293383">Fibonacci sample</a>. Running the
sample on my machine with <em>fibonacci(42)</em>, the result looks like this:</p>

<p><code>
Java: 1.43s
Groovy 1.8 or 2.0: 3.08s
Groovy 2.0 with indy: 6.55s
</code></p>

<h2>It's just the first step for Groovy</h2>

<p>It is good for Groovy to support invokedynamic, but the support is not
ready yet. Some code might benefit from it, but other does
definitively not. The JVM currently does not support all optimizations
the Groovy runtime already does.</p>

<p>Making the usage of invokedynamic difficult hopefully prevents people
from using it without knowing about the impacts. So we'll see, how
well Groovy and invokedynamic will work together in future versions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring and JSR 330 scopes]]></title>
    <link href="http://derjan.io/blog/2011/10/18/spring-and-jsr-330-scopes/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-18T07:09:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://derjan.io/blog/2011/10/18/spring-and-jsr-330-scopes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Spring 3 added support for
<a href="http://download.oracle.com/javaee/6/api/javax/inject/package-summary.html">JSR 330 configuration</a>,
so you can use <strong>@Named</strong> and  <strong>@Inject</strong> instead of <strong>@Component</strong> and
<strong>@Autowired</strong>. Unfortunately Spring's default scoping is not compatible with
JSR 330. Here is how it works:</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Default behaviour</h2>

<p>By default Spring uses it's default scoping behaviour on JSR 330 configured
beans like below.</p>

<p><code>java
@Named
public class GreetingService {
}
</code></p>

<p>This means, that <em>GreetingService</em> will become a bean with singleton scope.</p>

<h2>JSR 330 scopes</h2>

<p>In difference to Spring JSR 330 defines, that the default scope of beans is
prototype, which means a new object is created everytime it will be injected
somewhere. If you want a different scoping you can create your own annotation for
this like descriped
<a href="http://download.oracle.com/javaee/6/api/javax/inject/Scope.html">here</a>. JSR 330
already comes with a predifined scope annotation for
<a href="http://download.oracle.com/javaee/6/api/javax/inject/Singleton.html">singletons</a>. To
make Spring behave as specified in JSR 330, you can use a different scope
resolver like below.</p>

<p><code>xml
&lt;context:component-scan base-package="my.package"
  scope-resolver="org.springframework.context.annotation.Jsr330ScopeMetadataResolver" /&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Using this additional configuration, will make the above <em>GreetingService</em> bean
prototype scoped. To make it a singleton bean again, you will need to use the
singleton scope annotation.</p>

<p><code>java
@Named
@Singleton
public class GreetingService {
}
</code></p>

<h2>Custom scopes for JSR 330</h2>

<p>Spring comes with further scopes like <em>request</em> or <em>session</em>. JSR 330 does not
support them out of the box. You will have to create your own annotations for
this. Let's look, how to do this for the <em>request</em> scope.</p>

<ol>
<li>Create your own scope annotation:</li>
</ol>


<p><code>java
@Scope
@Documented
@Retention(RUNTIME)
public @interface Request {
}
</code></p>

<ol>
<li>Extend <em>Jsr330ScopeMetadataResolver</em> to map your annotation on Spring's
scope:</li>
</ol>


<p>```java
public class CustomScopeMetadataResolver extends Jsr330ScopeMetadataResolver {</p>

<p>  public Jsr330SpringScopeMetadataResolver() {</p>

<pre><code>registerScope(Request.class.getName(), WebApplicationContext.SCOPE_REQUEST);
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>}
```</p>

<ol>
<li>Use your custom resolver in your Spring configuration:</li>
</ol>


<p><code>xml
&lt;context:component-scan base-package="my.package"
  scope-resolver="my.resolver.package.CustomScopeMetadataResolver" /&gt;
</code></p>

<p>The above sample will make all beans, that are annotated with your own
<strong>@Request</strong> annotation request scoped.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
